[Music]
This is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
se-radio.net. SE radio is brought to you
by the ITE computer society and by it e
software magazine online at
[Music]
computer.org/software. Welcome to
software engineering radio. I'm your
host Gavin Henry and today my guest is
Matches Endler. Matches is a Rust
developer and open- source maintainer
with 20 years of experience who provides
training and consulting through his
company called Corrode. Beyond writing
clean code, he prioritizes creating
supportive environments where teams can
grow their rough skills together.
Matias, welcome to Software Engineering
Radio. Is there anything I missed in
your bio that you'd like to add? No,
that pretty much sums it up. Thanks for
having me, Kevin. Perfect. My pleasure.
So, I got you on the show because I saw
your blog post. really enjoyed it. It
was called prototyping in Rust. Yes. It
helped me understand how to take my idea
and try to validate it in Rust, which
isn't something you usually hear. So, I
thought I'd get you on to chat over your
techniques and go through some of the
things that might help other people get
into Rust for the first time or reach
for it when they want to do that
prototype. So, let's lay down some
foundations. Could you give me an
overview of what a prototype is?
Sure. Well, I like to compare it with
art. When you try to paint a picture,
you don't really have to start from the
top and go all the way to the bottom.
Usually, you try to capture the main
idea as quickly as possible before it
goes away. And so maybe you can start
with a sketch and a prototype is like a
sketch. It turns out that programming
itself is a very iterative process. We
do believe that when we read the program
in the end, the ideas are there and we
thought about these ideas from the get-
go, which is not true. In reality, we
also sketch out certain parts of our
application as we go. And this is what a
prototype is. It starts as a quick draft
of what we have in mind and then we
iterate on it. Thanks. And do we keep it
or do we throw it away? because I've
heard other explanations. I think it's
in the pragmatic programmer book where
they say a prototype is something you
bin. But I don't know. What do you
think? That's a good point. I think a
lot of people when they think about
prototypes, they have this idea of a
throwaway product or project in mind. We
will throw it away anyway. But I think
it's an orthogonal question that is
besides the question of whether to
prototype or not or what a prototype
looks like because in reality it doesn't
really matter. If you're happy with the
result, you can keep it. You can iterate
on it. But the main point is that you're
trying to get an idea from your brain
into some sort of text format. And this
is the main core idea. It helps you find
the best approach before committing to a
design. Whether you keep it or not in
the end is completely up to you,
completely up to the complexity of the
project, the team you work with and all
of these things that are maybe even
outside of your control. Maybe your
manager will say we will go forward with
it. And I would say that's a positive
thing even because you started with the
right idea but prototyping is like
hingching your risks because if you
start with the wrong idea you can
happily throw it away and you didn't
lose a lot of time. I like that
explanation. It also in my experience it
gives you a different mindset because
you're thinking this is a prototype. I
don't need to care too much about it. I
can you know whereas if you're starting
the real thing then you're thinking oh I
need to get this right I need to do this
I need to do that so maybe it's a bit
more freeing because it's got that label
on it right so should a prototype be in
the same programming language that we
think the final or production version's
going to be or should it just be
something that gives us that freedom or
what's your thoughts one huge advantage
of using the same language and the same
tool set especially
for the prototype and the final version
is that you don't have to go through the
rewrite. And the rewrite in quotes is
the process of going from your decent
idea to quote unquote production code.
Now, if you have to change the language,
then you might make mistakes or maybe
the patterns that you use in one
language, they don't translate to
another language. So you kind of end up
in a weird situation where maybe you try
to bite off too much or you probably end
up with two problems. One would be the
translation from one language to the
other and the other would be making it
ideatic again in the other language that
you chose for production. So I would say
if you can keep it in the same language
ideally you would want to use the same
language. And I think the other part is
the tool set. If you have a certain
stack for writing say a Python prototype
or a Golang prototype then this
translates very well into a Python
production application or a Golang
production application. Same for Rust.
The tooling is what makes developers
fast and what makes them efficient. And
if you have to switch the language, then
you also have to switch the tooling and
the entire ecosystem that goes around
with how do I put that into production.
For example, how do I containerize my
language or what CI/CD frameworks can I
use and whatever. So there is an
advantage to using the same language
ideally. It's not always possible in
every language, but I would strive for
it. Before I move us on to our example
application in the next section, I see
quite a few places where people say that
Rust isn't a good fit for this type of
process, i.e. prototyping. Why do they
say that? Yes, I fully agree that this
is a very common trope that I see being
repeated on public social media, on
YouTube, in various blog posts and so
on. the notion that Rust is not a good
language for writing prototypes in. And
this is kind of what prompted me to
write the blog post because what I see
in practice is not what people say on
the internet about this topic. And I
wanted to write some wrongs here if you
want. The reality is that my clients and
me, we are very effective with writing
prototypes in Rust. But to your
question, why do people think Rust is
not a good fit? I would say there's a
few misconceptions out there. First
would be that the Rust type system,
which is very strict, pushes back when
you change your mind. So it tries to
keep you in track. And when people think
about prototyping, they think about
running free, letting their ideas flow.
But in reality, they also want guard
rails. Even in this early process,
another misconception is that memory
safety and prototyping are incompatible.
ROS is a very safe language. It needs
you to know how to handle memory and it
forces you to use ownership in borrowing
and that takes the fun out of
prototyping and it's also incompatible
with what you want to build in the long
run. And I don't believe that is true
necessarily because you will have to
deal with that anyway and you might as
well just deal with it in the beginning
when you have the most control over it.
Another misconception is that Rust
requires getting all the details right
from the beginning. And I think that's
not entirely true. I think it wants you
to get the important details right. For
example, how do you structure your
strcts? And how do you manage ownership
of these objects that you can create
from these strcts? Who's owning what at
what point? What are the lifetimes of
your objects in your system? And these
are things that are very important even
for a prototype, but especially for
production because otherwise you would
introduce no pointers. And I think the
combination of all of these things would
be that Rust requires you to handle
errors and that gets in the way of
prototyping. Well, that's not entirely
true. There are escape hatches for
handling errors. Even in Rust, you can
use unrep, you can use expect, and you
don't really have to handle all of the
errors right away. It's just that Rust
will kind of panic in case it runs into
an error. And that's a good thing even
for a prototype. It means in reality you
can avoid all of these pitfalls while
getting the most value from Rust. Thank
you. Going back to your earlier point in
the answer about borrowing and ownership
and the fact that Rust pushes forward
things that you'd need to deal with
earlier. If you were doing this in a
scripting language or a dynamic
language, say, you might be just saving
debugging for later when you've saved
things to the same variable twice or
things like that. So you could argue on
the flip side that Rust helps you out
faster than these other languages
because it's telling you these problems
straight away and you shouldn't think
about it getting in the way. It's
actually helping you. Rust is very much
a dayto language and I think that's at
the core of the problem here where
people mostly start with their clean
pristine vanilla idea in their head and
then they have to face reality in which
some of their ideas don't make any sense
or some of the concepts they came up
with they don't really work well
together. And with many other languages
like Python, you defer those issues
until later. And later is usually when
rubber hits the road and when you make
the prototype into a production system.
Rust does not allow you to do that. So
the initial ramp up phase is much more
involved but on day two you can reap the
benefits because all of these conceptual
issues, all of these integration issues
are already solved. You kind of take
this burden away from your future self.
But what I see in other languages is
that people take on a loan of their own
future and it will haunt them later on.
But then later on is the painful time
that they don't have to think about
right now. Rust is very much against
that and tries to start from a clean
slate and tries to put the right
abstractions in place that you know will
work in the future. That's a much better
answer than I just gave. That's cool.
Did you just make up day two or is that
a common term? I didn't invent it. Some
other people might say Rust shifts
complexity to the left and by left they
mean to earlier stages of development
for example the development phase or the
ideation phase and prototyping is
somewhere in between I would say oh like
on a time graph left the start. Yeah.
And these are all I would say day one
problems. So how do I set up the
project? How do I get from my idea to
something that I can play around with?
And many other languages, they excel in
this area. Especially the scripting
languages, they allow you to run free.
They allow you to make mistakes. Rust
does not allow you to. And then later on
day two, which is in production, when
later on you have a null pointer issue
or you have a race condition, these
languages tend to fall apart. It depends
on what you build of course, but that's
what I commonly see that services become
hard to maintain. They become brittle.
Refactoring becomes very tricky to do.
You might be afraid to make too many
changes because you might break things.
Whereas in Rust, it's pretty much easy
going then because all of these things
were clarified up front and really what
you end up with is mostly business
problems or logic problems maybe. But
the core semantics of the language keep
you from going astray and keep you from
drawing yourself into a corner where
your only escape might be a rewrite.
Yeah. I mean, and also you can have a
program that is correct and compiles and
runs, but it doesn't do the right thing.
So, Rust does help with that as well.
Right, I'm going to move us on to our
next section. So, we've got an idea or I
have had an idea for a prototype. I
don't know how applicable it is to the
blog post, but why don't we think about
a weather station that takes various
real world feeds and displays them
initially on a command line and then
maybe a display in production. Do you
think that's a good fit for prototype?
Anything can be a good fit for a
prototype, but yeah, this one
specifically I like because it has a
couple of components. Excellent. So, in
your blog post, obviously the listeners
can't see the article just now and the
images, but I took a screenshot of what
you've called Rust prototyping workflow,
which is a fourstep workflow. Number one
being define the requirements. Number
two being add your types. Number three,
you've called borrow check which we'll
explore. And number four is fix clippy
lints which comes with rust that helps
you tidy up things. So would you like to
take us through that workflow? Sure. So
the first step would be to define your
requirements. By the way, this is just
my workflow. It's not a canonical
version of any workflow. I don't impose
that on anyone else. I just try to
explain what works for me in practice
and how I think about prototyping. No,
that's cool. That's cool. Sure. I just
thought it helped to describe things
nicely. Yeah. Yeah. Totally. In the
first stage, I try to define my
requirements and I don't really think
about the types as much as I think about
the components or how they interact. I
might not even write a single line of
code in that stage. I might just draw
something on a piece of paper or use
Excaliraw to draw a couple boxes and
lines and then just see how it feels,
how it feels in my head, how I could
imagine things going. I do think a lot
about control flow or data flow rather
than objects because I think you can
always model proper objects around your
data, but it's very hard if you do it
the other way around. And in this stage,
I usually just think about the larger
parts and how they would interact and
how they would communicate with each
other. And then I go to stage number
two, which is adding types. In Rust, of
course, you have a lot of types. For
example, we have I think like 20
different string types, and most people
are just aware of maybe two. Yeah, I'm
only aware of string new and borrowed
string amperand string. Yeah, it all
boils down to the guarantees that you
want to give about your string. Is it
UTF8? Is it on the heap or the stack and
so on. But in reality, you don't really
need to know about all of these
different string types. What you can do
is just use the most simple type that
would possibly work. And since Rust is
so typeheavy, it allows you to build
these abstractions from simpler
abstractions. And you can always add
more guarantees later on. With some
experience, you might even start with
the lowest of guarantees that you can
possibly give. But let's assume in the
beginning you have a message. Don't even
over complicate it. Just use a string.
Whether it lives on the stack or the
heap doesn't really matter. Whether you
allocate or not doesn't really matter at
this point. You just know a message is a
string. So you just use the own string
type with a capital S for example. Other
examples are you don't use of a slice if
you can use a vector or if you don't
know which integer type to use just use
an i32 for example don't think too hard
about the very specifics of the
implications of your types at this stage
because in the end you can replace them
with finer or more refined types so to
say. Now once you build up your little
system of types, you try to talk to the
compiler about it and there's this
notion of fighting with the borrow
checker. I think that's a misconception
as well. In reality, you discuss with
the borrow checker or you have a
conversation with the borrow checker.
This is how I see it nowadays. I like
it. So it might tell you, okay, look,
this doesn't work because this place in
memory does not live long enough. You
probably want to use a different type or
you have a smaller scope for that or
maybe you want to add a lifetime if
needed. But most of the time it would
just tell you this goes out of scope.
Try to make the scope larger so that the
variable lives for longer. Now after
this stage you know that you have two
things. You have types which model what
you want and you know that it will work
in production because the borrow checker
tells you if there are any null pointer
issues or any memory issues, safety
issues. And now the last part, part four
would be to refine and to improve and to
fix some of the code. And I use Clippy
for that a lot, as do many other people.
And Clippy gives you a lot of hints
about what to improve in your code. Just
set it to the highest level possible.
Even in prototyping, it's fine. And then
it will point out things that you can
improve and maybe that you did not know
about. But also with experience you will
see how you can probably shape it up
yourself during that stage. Fixing
clippy lens doesn't only mean that you
fix the clippy lens but also that you
fix everything and prepare yourself for
the next iteration cycle and start over
again with defining more requirements.
This is the cycle. Yeah. because I might
not have explained the image. It's a one
to four item list, but then it loops
back to number one. That's your workflow
process. Okay, let's go through that
again. So, we've defined the
requirements for the weather station. An
input might be the level of rain that's
happened. We think about a type for that
to keep it simple. We've chosen a
string. If we need to do a list of
things, we're going to reach for a
vector and not think too hard about
that. At this point, we'll have some
variables. We'll be moving stuff about
and we might compile the project and get
some complaints from the borrow checker
saying that we're using a variable in
another place and we haven't moved it
properly or we need to create something
else. Is that a good summary from 1 to
three so far? Yes. And there will be
errors which we haven't handled at this
stage. Yeah. Will it compile at.3? It
will compile on level three. But to make
it compile, we might still need to add
some escape hatches here and there. For
example, we could add a little to-do.
And there's a macro for this, which
actually is called to-do exclamation
mark. And then you can specify whatever
you need to do in this line. And this is
what I do a lot. I say, oh yeah, we need
to flesh out this part or here's a
little bit that's missing or this is
unimplemented. And that is completely
fine. And who are you telling that to
yourself or to? Oh well, this is in fact
an instruction in Rust. So this is a
language primitive that you can use
wherever you need to fill in gaps later
on. And the compiler will turn away at
this line and say okay if I hit this
line it would just panic and that is
completely fine because you get the
message which says this needs to be done
in order for this to work. So it's not
something that's just printed on the
screen for you to remember that you need
to do. It's actually it's like an
executable comment. It's like an
executable to-do. Yeah, I've not used
that much or at all. And the cool thing
about this also is that all of these
primitives are grapable. You can search
for to-do exclamation mark and will show
you all of the places where you use
that. Or you can search for unwrap or
you can search for expect and it will
show you all the places that you need to
fix up for this to go from prototype to
production. You see where the power is
now because in Python there is no such
thing. Every single instruction could
throw an exception and usually the
exceptions appear very deep in the call
chain and this makes it super tricky to
do later on. But since ROS is so
explicit, it will kind of force you to
at least add this line and it just helps
you keep track so that you don't forget.
You don't have to fix it right away. A
lot of people say it needs to be perfect
or it doesn't compile and that is not
true. Nice. So stage three, the borrow
checker is helping us out already. You
mentioned lifetime. So can you just one
sentence remind listeners of what that
is if they're not familiar with Rust and
the borrow checker. First off, don't
worry about lifetimes. I even wrote an
entire article about this. Okay. I don't
think I've actually ever used the
lifetime syntax myself yet in any Rush
that I've read. So I don't know if I'm
doing it right because I haven't done
that. The way I think about lifetimes is
it's like a label. It's another set of
variables that you can use. So for
example, you say you have a file handle
and this file handle points to a certain
file that you can read from and then you
have a reader which uses that file
handle. Now the file handle needs to be
alive for as long as the reader because
otherwise if the reader is trying to
read from the file handle and it's no
longer there then well that's a memory
safety issue that's a null pointer
essentially and so you just define you
guarantee to the compiler you say this
file handle will always be around for as
long as the reader is around and you can
in comparison to all the other languages
spell it out is text in the Rust
programming language. You can say tick a
which is just a shortcut but it can also
be tick reader and that means this is
the lifetime of a reader that I'm
referring to here and you give the file
handle the lifetime of the reader for
example and I guess that's the entire
metric here. That's something you're in
control of that you have to remember to
make sure it doesn't go out of scope.
Yes, but 99% of the cases the compiler
will infer it for you. It's just in the
cases where it's not sure about which
lifetime you mean specifically. Say
there's more than one option that it
will ask you to edit yourself. But there
are lifetime elition rules which allow
you to skip most of the work as long as
it's clear what you're referring to. If
there's just a single lifetime in scope,
then you don't really need to specify
that. Excellent. So now we're at number
four. We're going to use I presume cargo
clippy lint to help us clean up the
code. Now we don't have to do this, do
we? No. But it's a bit like cleaning up
the kitchen. So technically you don't
have to clean the kitchen after every
time you make dinner or so. But like the
next day or the day after there's a
couple smells and you probably want to
avoid that situation. It's probably much
better if you do a little bit of work on
a regular basis instead of doing a lot
of work all at once. I'm not sure about
the audience, but I'm really bad at
getting myself a huge chunk of time to
do household chores. And this is very
similar. I have a much easier time
fixing things as I go. I'm not sure if
this is true because I'm not a good
cook, but what I imagine good cooks to
do is keep the workplace clean while
they cook. So, they kind of do that more
or less automatically. It's second
nature to them. Someone please correct
me if this is wrong, but in my perfect
imagination of a good cook, this is how
I think about it. And I would rather
clean up after myself while I'm coding.
And I just fix those little clippy lins
or whatever. A lot of people that work a
lot with Rust, they love Clippy for
pointing out issues. You get addicted to
it. Yeah, I like it too. It's one of the
first continuous integration workflows I
put in my GitHub repositories. Yeah. So,
it cleans it up. Cool. We've got about 5
minutes left in this section. We've
skipped some of the questions I wanted
to ask, but we'll do them now. I think
that was a good overview of the
workflow. We've gone through some of the
key components that Rust gives us. So
some of the inbuilt macros are massive
part of the tool set which is what I
love about the Rust ecosystem. Mhm.
We've had a we chat about type inference
that is in mentioned in your blog post.
It is actually. Yeah. And how we can
skip some of our error checking by using
the expect and unwrap functions. Do we
need to think about heap and stack
stuff? Just now I think we decided that
we're just going to stick with strings
and vectors in our prototype. Yeah.
Yeah. Absolutely. Cool. So, one last
question before we move on or two. When
I got exposed to Rust in a previous
life, I remember there was an issue in
production which I was explained to that
the default stack size of 2meg wasn't
big enough. Now, I know we said we're
going to skip heap and stack for memory,
but what does that mean? Because I
haven't had a chance to ask anyone. That
the default 2meg size of the Rust stack
wasn't big enough. Yeah. So we will have
to look at the specifics of this error.
But in general, Rust like any other
language has a limitation on the things
that you can put into the stack. And the
stack is a certain section in memory
that just keeps growing until it reaches
a certain threshold. It's very fast.
Essentially, you don't really deallocate
memory. just move a program counter
around and it always points at the
latest thing that you put on the stack.
So you can think of it as like a stack
of cards and you just can put things on
top and then you can take a thing from
the top and this is what a stack looks
like in memory. Now if you run out of
stack that means the deck of cards is
exhausted. you cannot put any more cards
on the stack because well there are no
cards anymore. Now how this usually
happens is there's a very complex
operation which puts a lot of things on
the stack. Of course, 2 megabytes is
kind of a lot of memory if you only
have, for example, simple integer types
or so. You can put a lot of integers on
a two megabyte stack, but at some point
you will run out of it. And sometimes
this happens when, for example, you
reach a recursion limit when you call a
function over and over again and it puts
more things on the stack until
eventually you're exhausted. And what it
means is when you get the message ran
out of stack or so ran out of memory,
usually it points at a bigger problem
with the logic of your application.
Maybe you can restructure your code such
that it doesn't put that many things on
the stack or vice versa. You could put
things on the heap instead which is
pretty much unlimited in size. And how
do you think we could trigger this issue
in our weather station prototype? That
be too many inputs or it would have to
be a lot of inputs. But for example, one
potential way to trigger this would be
if you wrote a function which does
calculations on a lot of weather data.
And it's recursive in a sense that the
result of one calculation depends on
calling this calculation again with
maybe a reduced set of inputs and then
over time you kind of add things to the
stack until yeah you run out of memory
but then again I also want to point out
that for every function call you kind of
create a new stack frame. So it's not as
if there was a single stack. effect
every function gets its own stack and it
will be cleaned up after the function
returns. So it would have to be a thing
that puts stuff on the same stack over
and over again. Maybe weather
information and doing some computation
in a loop or so and then keeping the
stuff around for way too long and not
accumulating a sum but trying to keep
all of the individual measurements on
the stack for too long. Maybe that will
be one way. But yeah, I agree that it's
kind of a constructed example. Yeah,
thanks for the explanation. It's not
something I'd come across in other
languages. I don't know if that's just
because I've not hit that type of thing,
but well, it can happen in any language
really. So, Rust isn't special in that
regard. I suppose that's stack overflow
is it in the stack and all those types
of things. Exactly. That's a stack
overflow. Now, the reason why a lot of
people don't run into that in dynamic
languages like Python is that a lot of
things end up on the heap instead of the
stack. And most people don't really
think about the stack as a place where
they can put stuff. But in reality, it's
probably a very fast and convenient
option. And it's an order of magnitude,
maybe two, maybe three orders of
magnitude at times faster than the heap.
A heap allocation is very expensive. And
if performance matters, maybe you do
want to use the stack more and Rust
allows you to do that. Whereas in other
languages like Python, that's harder to
do. Perfect. So I'm going to move us on
now to our next section. And I want to
go over some of the libraries or third
party things that aren't in core rust
that can help us with our prototype. So
we're going to park the app and just go
through three crates that you mentioned.
So the first one would be anyhow. Now,
I've spoken a little bit about this with
Tim McNamara when we did the four levels
of errors in Rust, which I'll put a link
in the show notes for listeners, but
could you just take me through what
anyhow does for us and how it allows us
to get on with the idea of our
prototype? Yes. Anyhow is a bit of the
next stage after you are done with your
first initial prototype. You have all
your code in place but you use unrep and
expect in many places and you kind of
want to get rid of it but you are
working say on a CLI application like
your weather app and you don't really
have a consumer of the errors. You just
want to have cleaner error messages and
you want to handle them properly inside
of your CLI application so that you can
eventually print a string and say this
went wrong. And this is where anyhow
comes in. Anyhow, itself is just a
wrapper around whatever the ROSS
standard library provides around error
handling like the error trait. But it's
nice because it adds some conveniences
like the context method which allows you
to add context to any error that
implements the error trait. And this is
extremely powerful because instead of
panicking when you hit an unwrap, it
will bubble up the error to the caller.
And all you need to do is change the
function signature from no return value
to an anyhow result value and returning
an okay at the end of the function. And
then you can use the context macro and
the bail macro that it provides to
convey that there was an error without
panicking. And in the central place you
can then print the error for example and
exit the program cleanly. This is a very
effective way if you are writing a
command line application or a binary
that doesn't have any consumers on an
API side like a library does. So if we
left the unwrap function call or the
expect that would just crash the binary
and it would panic. Yes. And to create
production version of our application or
idea we don't want any of that cuz it
looks terrible and it doesn't tell us
what we need to know. Yes. And the step
from unrep to anyhow is extremely small.
You can do that with a simple search and
replace of unwrap with context and then
you return the result type. So you
change the function header. You return a
result from your function and suddenly
you converted that into proper error
handling. You do that in the leave nodes
in the functions of your application and
then in a central place where the error
bubbles up you can handle it and print
it and exit the program cleanly. And
again this is kind of the powerful part
that people forget about prototyping in
Rust. We started with a thing that was
crude on purpose because we focused on
other things and now we end up in a
place where things are relatively smooth
already. After this anyhow stage, I
would say this is kind of on the level
of a decent error handling situation in
many other languages like Golang for
example with the added benefit that we
started with a way dirtier version in
the beginning. We didn't really have to
litter our code with if error not equals
nil like in go or we didn't really be
scared about exceptions like in Python.
We just have it there explicitly in our
code. there was an unrep and now we
replace it with context or with baleo
and suddenly we end up with a much
better more robust application and also
we know exactly where to look to make
this change because we're replacing
potential things unwrap and expect so
it's a lot easier to push that out of
your head and move on to the next step a
lot of the critical parts in rusts are
keywords yeah so the next crate in the
list of three we've got so we've done
anyhow would be bacon it's not something
I've well I like bacon but it's not
something I've heard of in Rust. Can you
take me through that one? In languages
like Node, you have a watcher which
allows you to restart the application
when you make a change. And this is what
Bacon does. It's sort of the inofficial
successor of cargo watch, which I love
to use, but it's deprecated by now. And
Bacon does a similar job. It just
watches for changes. And the moment you
save a file, it would run whatever
command you decide to run. for example,
cargo run. That's kind of the default, I
guess. So, you save the file, it would
trigger an event that Bacon listens to,
and then it restarts your app. And it
has some additional conveniences. For
example, it has this nice 2E app, the
text user interface application, which
shows you everything that's going on
from the errors that get thrown from the
compiler messages. Yeah, I think it has
more functionality and it's kind of a
nice co-pilot or companion while you
code. It runs in a terminal and it just
sits there and you can iterate on your
code while you prototype. You don't
really have to command troll C and up
and enter all the time to restart your
application. Instead, it has got your
back. It always shows you the latest
version. In our case, when we built the
weather app, we might have a CLI
application and maybe we run one
specific command over and over and over
again. Well, Bacon can do this for us.
We just make the changes in the code,
compiles, it runs the command, we see
the output right away. We don't have to
wait. It's more than what you'd get in
an IDA like Rustover or Zed or something
where it's constantly building when it
sees a change. Yeah, idees are all about
reducing the feedback cycle time and
baking takes this one more step further
because when an IDE does not know what
to do after the program compiles, you
kind of have to run the application
yourself. But Bacon fills this gap. It
runs the application in the end and it
shows you the output. And so it's again
about reducing the feedback cycle which
is kind of the core part of having a
great prototyping experience. Yeah, for
us we might decide that the weather
station takes all the data in on the
command line but also has an API restful
API built-in web API and we've decided
to have a a library and a binary and the
binary calls that API so bacon could
keep calling the rest endpoint that
we're trying to parse JSON for or
something like that. Yeah. Yeah. A good
example. It's all about getting this
ripple-l like experience that you know
from other languages. Yeah. The third
one we got, so we've done anyhow and
bacon. Third one I liked was called
cargo script. What is that? I like to
share code with other people. And for
that to work, it needs to be
self-contained. Some people might know
the Rust playground. It's a web
application. You can write some code and
then you get a link that you can share
with other people. Cargo script is
similar, but you can run it locally. It
just runs scripts. You can add
dependencies at the top of your script.
You can say this depends on anyhow for
example and then it will be a crate that
you depend on like a normal dependency.
And then you can take this script, copy
it, send it to a friend or a colleague
and ask them to run it with a specific
command cog script itself and it would
produce the exact same output as it did
on your machine. And this is extremely
helpful for prototyping and tossing
ideas around. So I kind of like to use
that a lot. It's still a nightly
feature. You don't always have to use a
nightly compiler to use the nightly
feature. You can just say cargo plus
nightly to temporarily use the nightly
compiler. But then the experience is
kind of great. Another thing that I use
it for, which is kind of besides the
prototyping part, but I wanted to
mention it, is for blog posts and book
chapters, for example. All of your code,
since it's self-contained in this
script, can be some sort of unit test
for your article. So, you just put the
code next to your document and then you
might run it just to check that it still
compiles. And so you make sure that the
code that you have in your article is
always valid. And I kind of like it.
It's very hard to keep code working
while you iterate on a blog post just
like you iterate on a prototype. I used
it for both cases for prototyping and
for writing nowadays. And why couldn't
you just build a binary and give that to
your person? Because they can't see the
code, I suppose. Yeah. Because they
can't see the code. And if you were to
show them the code, then you would have
to send them a zip file because ROSS
project consists of many files, not only
a single source file, but also a source
folder and a cargo tommo at least.
That's a good point because it might
never grow beyond a RA script either.
And just um before I move on to
the final section, you mentioned the
word nightly. So for those that aren't
too familiar with the different builds
of Rust, could you just summarize that
for me? Rust has three main versions
that you can use. The most common
version is stable rust. That is what
most people I would say 90% of people
typically use on a daily basis. Then you
have the nightly version of Rust which
is a as the name says nightly build of
the Rust compiler. They have a CI/CD
workflow which always runs at night and
produces a version of the Rust compiler
that you can use which has the latest
features enabled so that you can test
them. It's a bit cutting edge so if you
don't want to go all the way you can
sign up for beta and you don't have to
really sign up. You just tell Rust up
for example to download it and then you
have features that are about to be
stabilized in there and you can also try
them right away. So these are the three
let's say releases of Rust that are
continuously maintained. Nice. And when
you say nightly, whose night on the
planet is that? H that's a good point.
American night, European or I don't
know. I would assume that it's wherever
AWS servers are. But nightly is a bit of
a term that just tries to express the
fact that it's a build that runs on a
daily basis. It can also run during the
day, of course. Now, why is it a nightly
build? why they call it this way. I'm
assuming I don't know but I'm assuming
that it comes from this old notion of
batch processing which also ran through
the night. So developers would end their
day and then the batch processing thing
would run through the night and then in
the morning they would have the results.
So it's a bit like this. Yeah. Where
your backups would run overnight and
things like that as well. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Perfect. Thank you. So our last
section I've called debugging and error
handling. Now, we've touched a little
bit on how we handle errors already
where we could mark somewhere in our
prototype, let's call it a prototype
script since we've mentioned cargo
script. Now, so just to summarize that
last section, we did anyhow bacon and
cargo script. Anyhow was for errors.
Bacon was for detecting changes in the
code and then cargo script is to put
everything in one file to share. So, if
we're thinking about our one file to
share, we might we've already mentioned
the to-do macro where we know we need to
do something and the script will sort of
crash there because we haven't done it.
What other errors could we get in our
prototype apart from not having
implemented something bad data or maybe
this is just nothing to do with our
prototype and just errors in general. Do
we need to think about that type of
stuff now in our prototype? What would
you recommend? Yeah, this is the core
idea of prototyping to really try and
squeeze out all of the error conditions
that we could possibly get hit with as
early as possible. We kind of take
whatever would await us in production
and we try to go through it now because
it's way less costly to handle all of
these situations. Now, let's talk about
the weather station example again. So
what can go wrong? Well, we need to read
those feeds from somewhere and that
somewhere might not be available right
now. That might be a normal network
error. How do we handle that? Then if
the server is available and it sends us
some weather information, can we read
it? Is it in the correct format? What is
in there? Can we transform it into an a
rust type? Maybe des serialize it with s
and what if not? How do we handle that
case? Do we need the data from every
single feed all the time or do we handle
it some other way? That's a business
decision to be made and s is a crate,
isn't it? A library. Yeah, si stands for
serialization deserialization and it's
the core crate for that job in Rust. Now
I wanted to go forward and say let's say
we were able to aggregate all of the
data from our feeds. Now we want to
display that information somehow. Well,
where do we display that information? In
what format do we display that
information? Can we even format the
information in a way we want? And maybe
is the output available if we print for
example to the terminal. Well, can we
lock stand it out to print to it? Even
all of these things might happen in a
real world system. What if we run out of
memory? What if the processing of data
takes too long or whatever? These are
things that will keep us from deploying
this application to production and
that's why we need to handle it right
then and there. And so I would say error
handling at this stage now is the very
central part of our job. What macros can
help us to achieve this or even
experiment to make sure we've covered
everything? Yeah. Well, let's start with
the most simple example, print line. I
use print line a lot. It's a macro
because it takes variable amount of
arguments and you can litter print lines
wherever you want at this stage just to
understand the program logic. You don't
really need a full-blown debugger at
this stage. The type system will guide
you and the rest you can just print. Now
what if you want to be more expressive?
Maybe you don't really want to just
print stuff. You also want to show the
file name, the line number. What can you
do? Well, in this case, there's a macro
called debug and it shows just that. It
shows you where exactly in your code
this message was sent. It shows you the
expression that it evaluated and the
value that it returned. Then there's the
to-do macro which we already talked
about. This is amazing for scaffolding
functions and marking incomplete parts.
Then you have the unreachable macro
which is similar but also a little
different in comparison to do. It says
this part shouldn't be reached. I am
aware that this is not done but we
should never get into this point.
Whereas in to-do you say we will get to
this point we just didn't get around to
fixing this yet. And then for testing
you have two macros which are I would
say kind of relevant. One would be
assert which is like a normal assertion
in other languages. It documents
invariance. And then you have debug
assert which defers expensive checks and
it's only available in debug builds
which sometimes is nice especially if
you have a prototype. You write some
code you add some assertions right then
and there just so that you're clear
about your invariance but you don't want
to publish that in production and you
might forget to remove these assertions.
just use debug assert and then yeah it
won't end up in the release build but
it's still going to be there for
debugging purpose later on. So two
points I'd like to focus on and ask
there. So there's a debug build of your
Rust application and there's a release
isn't there? Yes de is bigger
potentially slower got lots more stuff
in it so you can debug it and release is
as fast as you can get. Everything's
slick streamlined and unreachable. Can
you give me a use case when we would use
that unreachable macro? I kind of get
it, but could you give me another
example? Yeah, I did write a MOS 6502
emulator at some point. You must have
been bored.
Yeah, my original goal was to build a
Nintendo Entertainment System emulator,
but in reality, the MOS 6502 was the
more interesting part, and I wanted to
get this right. So I started to write
out what an emulator does. So it takes
an instruction and then it transforms
that into machine code or in the case of
an emulator it just modifies the state
of the CPU. And what I found was that
there were undocumented things in the
CPU and these instructions were there
but they were not supposed to be
executed. Those were kind of maybe bugs
in the hardware or at least undocumented
in the MOS 6502 documentation. But I
just wanted to express the fact that
this section in the code should be
unreachable for any normal usage. And if
someone reached that point, that would
definitely be unusual. And I would not
want to care about this situation
because you kind of enter the realm of
undefined behavior. And I wanted to stay
clear from that. But this was a really
really nice use case for the unreachable
macro to say, "Yeah, this CPU
instruction might exist, but it should
be unreachable. I wanted to mark it." Do
you have the that code or the feature in
your application to satisfy something
else and then you just mark it not
useful? I don't understand why you have
that code around in the first place if
it's never going to get used. Yeah,
because Rust kind of forces you to tell
it what to do in specific cases like
pattern matching. For example, you have
an enum variant and it has four
different variants and one of them you
kind of don't expect to handle at this
stage. You can add a to-do if you say I
don't get around to doing this right
now. Or you can add unreachable to say
this should never happen and it should
never be reached. But Rust the compiler
itself kind of wants an answer from you.
It doesn't accept no as an answer or
returning a null pointer or just going
into undefined behavior. here in reality
what you say to the compiler is look if
we reach a spot please panic and then I
need to handle this in the future but
right now I don't want to deal with this
case yeah so you're satisfying its
requirement for understanding what to do
rather than just saying unwrap or
something cuz that's not acceptable yes
pattern matching in Rust is exhaustive
in the best sense and it needs you to
handle all of the variance that can
possibly occur that's why Rust is great
for error handling, isn't it? Yeah,
that's part of the reason for sure.
Yeah. Okay, so we've gone through some
great macros, some that I wasn't aware
of either. So, are there any normal Rust
things as in what you'd expect to see in
every production grade Rust application
that we should avoid at this point? I
would say three things. The first one
would be avoid generics. Just use
concrete types until it's really
necessary. Generics are maybe some
people don't know a form to say this
function can take a set of different
inputs. For example, it can take a
string or it can take an
integer. And sometimes this is really
helpful where you say this can take any
type that implements this trait. So it's
like an interface which says this for
example takes anything that can be
converted into a vector. And there's
various things that can be converted
into a vector and then you have to write
this function once but this gets in the
way of prototyping. I would say use
concrete types wherever possible. You
can also copy paste the function make
your modifications because more often
than not these two functions that you
created are different in nature and as
the prototype evolves you will find that
they look similar but they are
different. So they diverged and if you
added a generic too early on in your
program, you might not have the patience
or the insight to see that right away
and then you're bound with whatever the
design was at this point. So only
introduce generics when clear patterns
emerge and also just in general avoid to
be fancy. Don't add those generic type
signatures like tsrefster or so if it's
not necessary. Now the second part would
be avoiding lifetimes. We also covered
that already. Lifetimes just sidestep
them with cloning things and yeah the
borrow checker will be happy and you can
later grab for clone and improve your
code again. Also in case where you think
about multi-threading maybe an arc mutxt
is all you need really. You don't really
need to make your code thread safe right
away. You can just put it into an arc
mutx. So focus on the logic first. What
is cloning? Sorry, before we do version
three. Yeah. So cloning creates an
actual clone of a memory block on the
heap. So you have a string on the heap.
It owns some memory. You clone it. Then
you have another string that points
somewhere else on the heap, but it has
the same input. It has like it has the
same nature. It's also a string. It has
the same length. It has the same
contents, but it's like an actual clone
of your value. And the arc is a way to
have a copy of a variable that's unique,
isn't it? Yes. An arc is an atomic
reference counted value. And an atomic
is a way for the CPU to
enforce exclusive access to memory. And
with an ARC and especially the
combination of ARC mutx, you can
sidestep a lot of situations where you
would have to add lifetimes to your
variables. And in this case, you just
say, well, it is behind an arc mutex. So
it will be locked. It will be exclusive
to one owner that modifies the memory at
one point in time. But there cannot be
two writers at the same time in that
region in memory. So we want to avoid
generic lifetimes. And there was a third
one, wasn't there? Yes. The third one
that I like to do is to keep my
hierarchy flat. Earlier we talked about
cargo script and we can take this one
step further. I keep everything in my
main RS and when I need a module I just
use the mod keyword which is another
keyword in ROS and I can add the module
right in the same file in my main RS
because modules are not bound to files
as they are for example in go they are a
separate concept you can have multiple
modules in the same file and I used that
very very often so there there's no need
for complex organization you probably
don't know the names of things right
away and it would be hard later on to go
from a very nested hierarchy to a flat
hierarchy. So I keep it flat and I
experiment with the structure in the
same file. Once I feel confident that
this is the structure I want to go for,
I can always move modules into separate
files when the structure stabilizes.
Yeah, it's a good indicator like you're
saying where you search the source code
to replace unwrap with anyhow and some
context or etc. You just don't have to
think about it now. Yeah. Yeah. And do
you have a rule of thumb for when you
would want to put something in a new
file? Usually when I try to transition
from prototype to production. So this is
when I gradually replace the unwraps
with proper error handling and then I
think about structuring modules. Then I
think about
encapsulation. I think about composition
instead of inheritance. How do I make
these parts talk to one another? What
are the guarantees? What's the minimal
interface that I can provide? And how
can I put the rest into a module and
make it private? So this is the stage
from prototype to production where I
refine the type structure as I improve
my understanding. Yeah. Also have the
test located within that file
potentially as well. So it make helps
you switch context completely to focus
on. Yeah, exactly. And also adding
documentation. Yeah. And replacing old
types with references where appropriate.
Now is the time to do all of this extra
work to really understand, okay, how
should my hierarchy look like? And that
would be a good use case for that bacon
crate as well. If you're writing
documentation in that file that you've
just moved away from main RS cuz you
could refresh the browser to make sure
it's looking good. Yeah, you wouldn't
see the documentation in bacon, but
there is a cargo doc command. And this
is also the stage where I look at this
and see how does my documentation look
like? Is it clear? Do I need to be more
specific? Do I need Does that open a
browser for you? Yes. Oh, I didn't know
that. Actually, I remember now. Yeah, I
was just thinking it might refresh the
browser for you like tools. You can say
cargo do open. It opens the browser.
Yeah, I've actually written about that
as well. I just forgot. Super helpful.
Okay, well let's start wrapping up. I
think that was a really good walk
through picking what to leave and what
to take, what to focus on, and I
certainly learned a lot. So, I'm really
glad we did this show and thanks for
coming on. I hope it helps others
understand that you can actually
prototype in Rust. You can have an idea,
you can play around, you can share the
code, you don't have to think too big,
too hard, too early. Was there anything
that we missed you think would be good
time to talk about? Yeah, I think for
all the people that have a tendency to
optimize prematurely, you must try
really, really hard to write slow Rust
code. Rust is an excellent prototyping
language despite all of the wrong
perceptions. So don't really think about
performance too much when you think
about prototypes. Let the type system
guide you. You can always go in and make
things faster with profiling in the long
run, but you can never get back the
right abstractions once you go overboard
and use null pointers in other languages
or you do all of these anti-atterns. So
yeah, let the type system force better
design on you up front and I would
assume you need fewer iterations from
prototype to production with Rust. At
least I would encourage everyone to give
it a try. Excellent. So how could people
get in touch or reach out if they want
to work with you or just play around
with some of your ideas or have a chat?
Yeah, people can go to corro.dev.
This is where they can learn more about
the services that I provide. You can
look through the blog posts. We also
have a podcast about Rust usage in
production. It's actually called Rust in
production. A very fitting name. Yeah,
it's really good. I like it a lot.
There's my email address on there. And
yeah, feel free to reach out. Even if
you don't want to have a very long
running project, it's sometimes good to
have another pair of eyes, especially
when you go from prototype to
production. Just see if everything is in
place and we keep it very lean and take
it from there. Matus, thank you for
coming on the show. It's been a real
pleasure. This is Gavin Henry for
Software Engineering Radio. Thank you
for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by E
Software Magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at
se-radio.net. To provide feedback, you
can comment on each episode on the
website or reach us on LinkedIn,
Facebook, Twitter, or through our Slack
channel at
seradio.slack.com. You can also email us
at
teamseradio.net. This and all other
episodes of SE Radio is licensed under
Creative Common License 2.5. Thanks for
listening.